<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-28T17:16:30+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Autism Mom</title><subtitle>Autism mom; for autism and down syndrome mommies</subtitle><entry><title type="html">when will it unravel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/when-will-it-unravel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="when will it unravel" /><published>2017-03-02T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-03-02T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/when-will-it-unravel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/when-will-it-unravel">&lt;h1 id=&quot;when-will-it-unravel&quot;&gt;When Will It Unravel?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’m just negative but probably I just know my children too well.  When things go too smoothly I wonder, when is this going to unravel?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday morning both boys woke up at reasonable times.  They both got dressed without argument, sat down for breakfast without a complaint.  They got their teeth brushed and put their shoes on.  I even, (gasp of delight), brushed my teeth without anybody fighting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could I enjoy the moment?  Yes.  It was like a decadent chocolate.  I needed to be savored and enjoyed.  Not only had the kids been well behaved but we were going to be on time today!  Everything was perfect. But like all delicious chocolates, wonderful moments melt and fade away into reality.  This thought sat in the back of my mind as I loaded the kids in the car.  When is this going to fall apart?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started with the smallest complaint.  Just a whine.  “I want my bunny.”  And then my refusal, “I’m sorry, we don’t have time to get it. You already have 3 blankets.”  And then, like pulling a loose thread in a sweater, it all unraveled.  The storm clouds rolled in. Thunder and lightening boomed and flashed in the garage as I tried to get a screaming little boy into his car seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know people say, “Enjoy those times when they’re little.  They go by too fast.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that the years fly by fast but I can’t figure out why moments when the kids scream at the top of their lungs seem to go by more slowly than the good times.  Listening to a child scream in close confines for 30-45 minutes at a time is akin to torture.  I might be more tolerant of such behavior if it wasn’t how I spent the majority of the time with my children. It might even be humorous (haha, remember that one time when the little one threw a tantrum at the restaurant) if I had a few less stories like this to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day.  One day we’ll get into that car and there’ll be no drama. When that day comes I will burn it into my memory, “The perfect day.  The day when things didn’t unravel.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When Will It Unravel?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">wandering</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wandering" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="wandering" /><published>2017-02-28T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-28T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wandering</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wandering">&lt;h1 id=&quot;wandering&quot;&gt;Wandering&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently read an article on the Interactive Autism Network website that discussed how half of people with autism will bolt from places. Bolting is dangerous safety issue that can cause stress for families.  The stress pierces the heart at several angles.  The most obvious concern is: where did my child go and will they find their way back?  Another concern is:  Will he do this again?  Yet another concern:  What if a stranger picks him up?  And another concern:  Did I tell enough neighbors about my child so that in case this happens again, they can bring him back to the house?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report I read indicated that a greater number of children with ASD wandered when they were under 10.  The report also indicated that &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; non-asd siblings wandered out of their houses.  The number of children who wandered decreased over time.  The most interesting part of the report was the graph that showed the parent’s perception of their child’s state of mind when they wandered.  Most parents felt that their child was in a positive state of mind.  Very few parents felt that the child was agitated or sad when then wandered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-be-done-to-help&quot;&gt;What Can Be Done To Help&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wandering/img_2518/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/IMG_2518-150x150.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wandering www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Talk to your child about his or her wandering.  Explain that if they wander too far it will be difficult to find them.  Explain that it scares you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talk to your neighbors about your child and his tendency to wander. Ask them to bring him back to the house if they ever see him or her wander alone again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Buy a “medical-alert” necklace or bracelet. There are many options available that will custom engrave the necklace with the name address and phone number for the child.  There are necklaces of every shape, size and color.  There are bracelets made of plastic, metal or cloth (or a combination).  Depending on your child’s sensory sensitivities, you can find the right ID necklace or bracelet online.  Our favorite source is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.americanmedical-id.com&quot; title=&quot;American Medical ID&quot;&gt;American Medical ID&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Write a social story about wandering.  Be sure to explain that wandering from the house isn’t ok.  Offer a replacement behavior, for example: “When I feel like wandering, I will ask an adult to go on a walk with me. If they don’t have time, I will find something to do at home.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; If you have a behaviorist, talk to them about the wandering.  See if they have any suggestions to deal with this stressful problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Communicate with your spouse or other care giver, where the children are at all times.  If they seem too quiet, it is often to good to be true.  Keep on high alert constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-story&quot;&gt;Our Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a beautiful spring day last year, I was all suited up for a jog.  I had my jogging shorts, running shoes and sweat wicking shirt on.  I had programed my iPhone full of music I loved.  As I left the house, I said goodbye to my sons and husband.  The only problem was that D followed me out into the garage:  He wanted to go on a jog, too.  I told him that I was going alone and to go back in the house.  I plugged my earphones in and started jogging up the street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t long before we discovered I had a follower.  I walked him back to the house and told him to go inside.  This is where I made my first mistake.  I should have walked him in the house and told my husband that he wasn’t invited on the jog.  Instead, I assumed that he went back in the house.  Well, he didn’t go back in the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we asked him about it later, D told us that he was jogging with me.  I, however, have no recollection of having a jogging buddy. When I got home, D was sitting on the couch(red faced and still panting) with my husband who asked me where “we had gone jogging.  I told him that “we” didn’t go jogging.  It wasn’t long before we figured out that D had left the house and run nearly a mile away from home and back completely by himself. We also realized that he had to cross several streets unassisted. Thank goodness that child has an incredible sense of direction.  The whole incident shook us up pretty good.  We promptly purchased an ID tag in case he ever tried “running” again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, the runner struck again.  My husband had gone on a walk with our youngest son.  D wanted to go with them.  I assumed that he was going with my husband.  My husband assumed he was staying home.  About 2 blocks later, he heard somebody shuffling behind and found D trailing behind.  D hadn’t asked me permission and hadn’t told his dad that he was going. He just ran off by himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each time it happened, that fear of… what might have happened crept into our minds.  Thank goodness we live in a nice neighborhood with understanding people.  Things ended up fine but the families who deal with this on a more frequent basis must be stressed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more about wandering you can check out the report at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iancommunity.org/cs/ian_research_reports/ian_research_report_elopement&quot;&gt;http://www.iancommunity.org/cs/ian_research_reports/ian_research_report_elopement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Wandering</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">top 10 things i am thankful for</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/top-10-things-i-am-thankful-for" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="top 10 things i am thankful for" /><published>2017-02-26T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-26T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/top-10-things-i-am-thankful-for</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/top-10-things-i-am-thankful-for">&lt;p&gt;It is that time of year, when we take stock of the things in life that we’re thankful for.  Please share what you’re thankful for at the end of the post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-my-children&quot;&gt;2.  My Children&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I thought having kids was all about playing games with them, doing holidays up for them and going to the park.  Boy was I wrong.  My kids have already put me through the ultimate lessons in child psychology.  I have learned so much about kids, myself and how to get us to work together as a team. My kids have taught me how to be more patient than I ever thought possible and the deepest love I have ever known.  My kids have led me to discovering what is most important in life: their well being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-my-family&quot;&gt;3.  My Family&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we might have one of the smallest families (and extended families) ever but you couldn’t find a more caring group of people.  My parents and in-laws are loving , caring and accepting of my children for who they are.  My brother’s sense of humor always brings me back to “real” place. He’s hilarious.  My only wish is that I had more time to see everyone, cousins, aunts, uncles and immediate family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-good-friends&quot;&gt;4.  Good Friends&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am blessed with more wonderful friends than a person could hope for.  Friends who are understanding of our circumstances in life and love us anyways.  So to all of those awesome people who invite us over but know that things might end with a kid throwing a tantrum: thank you!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-health&quot;&gt;5.  Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health problems seem to be a negative a recurring problem in my family’s life.  Without turning this post negative, I want to offer my thanks for every day when good health and healing are in our favor.  Good health is the best wealth.  Good health is worth more than all the money in the world.   When your life is turned upside down by medical problems without any obvious solutions, no amount of money in the world can change things back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-kind-strangers&quot;&gt;6.  Kind Strangers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice people make my heart smile.  Thank you to everyone out there who does their best to make the world a better place through random kind deeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-mistakes&quot;&gt;7.  Mistakes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistakes are short term setbacks that create opportunities to learn something new.  For every major mistake I’ve made, I’m thankful for the lessons learned.  Mistakes offer new opportunities and chances for growth and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-good-books&quot;&gt;8.  Good Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slipping into somebody else’s world for a while is relaxing and therapeutic.  Good books are one of life’s greatest treasures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-nature&quot;&gt;9.  Nature&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/2011-06-18-21.27.43.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/2011-06-18-21.27.43-150x150.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset&quot; title=&quot;Sunset&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going camping, hiking, walking, jogging or playing in the great outdoors is a blessing.  Nature is wild and beautiful with her deserts, mountains, sea shores, valleys and myriads of other landscapes.  She is untamed and beautiful; a force to be reckoned with.  Nature is a gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-lifes-challenges&quot;&gt;10.  Life’s Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a bump in the road we might have the ill conceived notion that life is simple.  Learning to deal with ongoing challenges with grace makes us kind, thoughtful and compassionate of others.  So say a little prayer of thanks to the challenges in life.  The challenges help us realize there is a big world out there filled with people who are experiencing similar things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list could go on and on since there are so many things in life that are fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Thanksgiving, everyone!  I encourage you to add to this list below!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is that time of year, when we take stock of the things in life that we’re thankful for.  Please share what you’re thankful for at the end of the post!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the inspiration to write</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-inspiration-to-write" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the inspiration to write" /><published>2017-02-24T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-24T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-inspiration-to-write</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-inspiration-to-write">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-inspiration-to-write&quot;&gt;The Inspiration to Write&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The well of inspiration to write has dried up like a desert.  It has become too difficult to find the time or enthusiasm for it at this time.  While I likely won’t be adding many, if any more blog entires at all, I plan to keep this site up for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was adding posts on a daily basis, my goal was to write informative, positive (mostly) and /or humorous vignettes and articles on the subject of autism. Since the articles are still viewed frequently I will keep things rolling along (doing basic management of the site through updates etc.).  I will not respond to any of the comments so I will remove ALL comments from now on.  Please don’t spam my site with garbage linkbacks.  There are none allowed on my site now, nor will there ever be.  To the considerate commentator, I won’t be checking comments or the email associated with this site.  Just reading my articles is will need to be enough &lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_smile.gif&quot; alt=&quot;:-)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for reading my stories and spreading the positivity about autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am one fortunate mom to be blessed with two fantastic sons; to be given such unique perspectives of the world through two different little people’s eyes…  From the same parents but totally unique in their thoughts and perceptions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our life keeps going, just as lives do.  Things get better, as everything does in life.  Hopefully one day I will take back my enthusiasm for writing prolifically. At this time, I have dedicated my time to other pursuits.  Thanks for your support and happy reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Inspiration to Write</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">thank goodness for real people</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thank-goodness-for-real-people" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="thank goodness for real people" /><published>2017-02-22T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-22T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thank-goodness-for-real-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thank-goodness-for-real-people">&lt;h1 id=&quot;thank-goodness-for-real-people&quot;&gt;Thank Goodness For Real People&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had arrived home after a very long, very frustrating commute.  After a full day of working and an hour and 45 minutes on the road (one hour longer than the regularly scheduled commute), I was beat and hungry.  I pulled out the left-overs from the fridge while my oldest continued his behavioral therapy.  Microwaved and steaming, the half of a burrito I didn’t eat last night made my taste buds water.  Just as I sat down to eat my son’s case manager sat down for a little bit of conversation over dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discussed the recent problems D had been having during behavior therapy.  His behavior has been steadily declining over the last few months.  She said that she and the therapists had recently met to discuss ways to remedy the problem. They thought if maybe they took some of the pressure off and we just had one of the therapists hanging out with us in the evenings, it might be a place to start.  The overwhelm, which I can usually hide but struggled to disguise after a long day, crept onto my face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structure added to our evenings, when I am so severely structured at school sounded like more work that I couldn’t muster at 5pm.  It isn’t as if things are a big free for all at our house in the evening, it’s more like there’s a general plan that shifts and changes as the evening presses on.  I think of it like a ball of clay.  We shape the evening out in general terms (dinner, baths, bed time stories, homework, playing, making lunches) but it doesn’t happen at a specific time or in a specific order.  Like clay, we add more embellishment to our evening as our creativity allows us. Feeling as if it needed to be structured or formulaic would take the life out it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t say that to his case manager. She smiled and looked at me.  She knew.  She absolutely knew what I was thinking as I tried to explain that we’re rather free form with our evenings and that I wasn’t sure how I could incorporate someone into our regular evenings.  Thankfully she came up with some more options that seemed like they would mesh better with what we’re  doing in the evening and allow us to have an important role in the therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/2013-03-17-17.19.53.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/2013-03-17-17.19.53-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2013-03-17 17.19.53&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;As the conversation came to a close, and as I took the last few bites of burrito, she said to me, “You know, I totally understand where you’re coming from.  Here I am barging into your house telling you what to do and here you are thinking, ‘I’ve already tried that, why do you keep asking me to do those same things over and over.’  It is hard to know how to advise you because you come from a similar background as me.  You’re around children, you have an education in child development and here I am telling you what you already know.  Many of our parents don’t have this same background and I have to remind them over and over about things,” she grinned at me, “But you–”  She was interrupted by my children attacking each other and screaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We both sighed and I rolled my eyes and said, “Thank goodness there’s a cold beer waiting in the fridge for me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I thought, thank goodness for the real people of the world.  The ones who get that you aren’t perfect.  The ones who know you know better, you’ve tried it, you do it but your kids still act like hooligans despite your best efforts.  They understand the frustration of being an educator with a beautiful child who seems so typical sometimes that his autism comes across as a case of bad parenting. They don’t judge, they just love you no matter what… even if you plan to sip a cold one while your children scream at each other.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Thank Goodness For Real People</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">staying ahead of the game</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/staying-ahead-of-the-game" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="staying ahead of the game" /><published>2017-02-20T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-20T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/staying-ahead-of-the-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/staying-ahead-of-the-game">&lt;h1 id=&quot;staying-ahead-of-the-game&quot;&gt;Staying Ahead Of The Game&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There couldn’t have been a better day for a school carnival.  The temperature hung at about 85 degrees while kids ran, clad in shorts and sandals, across the lawn. There were multiple jumpy houses, a rock wall, a blow up mechanical bull ride, a human sized hamster wheel, games, a photo booth, a miniature train that gave rides around the school, a reptile exhibit, an ambulance you could sit inside of, the local fire truck that you could sit in, two food trucks parked at the edge of the field and a cake walk.  What more could a kid ask for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We walked to the carnival from our house at around 5pm, when the crowds were fairly small. The first jumpy the boys went in had no line because it was meant for the younger kids.  They spent a while leaping around, attacking the blow up animals inside the farm themed jumpy.  Then the youngest noticed the much larger jumpy slide.  He leaped out of the barnyard jumpy and started running full bore, without shoes, across the lawn toward his destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is so much like my youngest.  He runs headlong towards whatever he wants without thought of consequences of his actions. Can you tell he is three years old?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/IMG_3113.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/IMG_3113-224x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lizards www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;While the visual of this moment might be kind of funny: a little blonde boy running across a field with his mother yelling behind him and his older brother getting upset because he is trying to get his shoes on and being left behind, it was kind of not funny.  By the time I caught the little guy, he had already run across the field to the line of the jumpy he wanted to go on.  D was trailing behind us wearing socks and carrying his shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blare of the generators that kept the jumpy houses inflated was slightly overwhelming for me but if it bothered D, he hid it very well.  He was so excited about going on the jumpy slide that he kept running out of line.  As a mom who isn’t interested in waiting in the same line for hours on end, I held his spot and reminded him many, many, many times to stay in line or else he’d lose his spot.  Once the boys reached the front of the line on the jumpy slide, D hesitantly went in.  He climbed and then slid down. Climbed up and slid down.  While it wasn’t audible at first, people were starting to get annoyed. I asked him to come out. He did.  Then little brother went in, full speed ahead.  D was so bothered that little brother could do this that he went in after him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 5 minutes of waiting, neither of the boys emerged from the maze of inflatable obstacles.  Since the lady monitoring the  slide looked visibly perturbed, I asked if I could go in after them.   Before I went in a parent looked at me and said, “Hmm, my kids were waiting forever behind yours and they went in and came out before yours did.”  With that positive comment, I went in after them.  I found little man at the end of the maze climbing a Mount Everest type of rope climb to the top of a really tall slide.  I pushed him up to the top where he slid down with glee.  I climbed to the top and saw that D had just slid down.  Down I went, big kid on a jumpy house slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/IMG_3110.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/IMG_3110-224x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;human hamster wheel www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The boys had a great time jumping, playing and running.  And then things started to change.  The change was almost instantaneous.  A light switch that was turned off.  I noticed it right after D pet the enormous tortoise (that acted like a lawn mower in his penned off area of the carnival).  I had two carnival tickets left and asked the boys if they wanted to go on one last train ride.  D screamed no.  Probably would have been a good idea to take that as a hint.  But like all tragic moments, hindsight is 20/20.  I herded the boys off to the train.  When I loaded them on, D started getting within 2 inched of little brother’s face and yelling at him.  I had to break up the fight several times before the train left on it’s voyage around the outskirts of the school.  I probably should have seated them in different seats but the ride was crowded. So I had faith that things would be ok and sent them on the ride alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I heard it.  Little brother’s scream and D right up in his face yelling at him just as they rounded the corner out of my sight.  I’m pretty sure I heard another yelp but couldn’t be sure it was little brother.  When the ride stopped, little brother was crying his eyes out, D was yelling and I could feel embarrassment tinging my cheeks red.  I swept the little one up in my arms and walked home.  D trailed behind, with a mixture of complaints and mean comments yelled as loud as he could muster. I walked as fast as I could with my youngest in my arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon arrival home the boys were promptly dressed in jammies and sent to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My husband and I talked about it later.  I was so disappointed in D but my husband brought up a good point, he had been very good for the majority of the carnival.  The last 2o minutes wasn’t really representative of how he behaved for the other 2 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wish I had just let those $2 orange tickets go and walked home when D was ready.  We should have left while we were still ahead of the game.  But in all reality, the boys will remember the fun times and the tantrum will be buried in the recesses of my mind.  It will be a reminder that things can go from good to bad in less than a minute.  And just as fast, I can help things change for the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Staying Ahead Of The Game</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">social stories resources</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/social-stories-resources" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="social stories resources" /><published>2017-02-18T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-18T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/social-stories-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/social-stories-resources">&lt;h1 id=&quot;social-stories-resources&quot;&gt;Social Stories Resources&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a list of several online resources for pre-made or easy to customize social stories.  I’ll be updating this page as I find other great resources (both paid and free)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sandbox-learning&quot;&gt;Sandbox Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sandbox-learning.com&quot; title=&quot;Sandbox Learning&quot;&gt;Sandbox Learning&lt;/a&gt; has excellent social stories that can be highly customized.  Because their stories are very high quality, they charge a yearly fee for each story you need.  The rates are reasonable and if you teach special education, having access to certain stories for a whole year can be very beneficial.  Some of the topics they cover are: Trying new foods, going to the doctor, using hands appropriately, feeling frustrated, making good choices.  There are many more topics available on their site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;easy-social-storiescom&quot;&gt;Easy Social Stories.com&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://easysocialstories.com/SocialStories.htm#stories&quot; title=&quot;Easy Social Stories&quot;&gt;Easy Social Stories&lt;/a&gt; provides high quality, paid social stories.  The author is interested in helping parents with what they need so contact her if you don’t see a story that meets your individual needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;carol-gray&quot;&gt;Carol Gray&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for excellent gold standard social stories, then check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://thegraycenter.org/index.php?page=shop.browse&amp;amp;category_id=16&amp;amp;vmcchk=1&amp;amp;option=com_virtuemart&amp;amp;Itemid=54&quot; title=&quot;The Gray Center&quot;&gt;Carol Gray’s site&lt;/a&gt;.  Her site has social stories and many other resources including how to write social stories and other tips.  Her books are not free but well worth the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;awesome-autism-social-stories&quot;&gt;Awesome Autism Social Stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my site where I am writing downloadable social stories.  Most cost $5.00 or less. I can tell you that include high quality writing and have great photographs.  Please check out my site at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.awesomeautismsocialstories.com&quot; title=&quot;Awesome Autism Social Stories&quot;&gt;http://www.awesomeautismsocialstories.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2307.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2307-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Social Stories www.autismmom.com&quot; title=&quot;Social Stories www.autismmom.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-skills&quot;&gt;Social Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you scroll halfway down &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.angelfire.com/pa5/as/socialskills.html&quot; title=&quot;Social Stories&quot;&gt;this web page&lt;/a&gt; there are some great free, printable social stories.  It is worth checking out for some free social stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-watson-institute&quot;&gt; The Watson Institute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thewatsoninstitute.org/teacher-resources2.jsp?pageId=2161392240601226415747290&quot; title=&quot;The Watson Institute&quot;&gt;The Watson Institute&lt;/a&gt; is a school in Pennsylvania that has a page dedicated to social stories.  The stories are free and downloadable.  They can be customized on Word.  These stories mainly use icons that are easy to understand, paired with words and pictures that you can insert into the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;child-behavior-guidecom&quot;&gt;Child Behavior Guide.com&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.child-behavior-guide.com/free-social-stories.html&quot; title=&quot;Child Behavior Guide&quot;&gt;This site&lt;/a&gt; has several social stories to choose from.  You have to scroll half way down the page to get to the stories, however.  If you need free social stories, this might be a good place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kids-can-dream-autism-web-site&quot;&gt; Kids Can Dream Autism Web Site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kidscandream.webs.com/page12.htm&quot; title=&quot;Kids Can Dream Autism Web Site&quot;&gt;This site&lt;/a&gt; was made by a young lady who has two brothers on the spectrum.  She has compiled a list of resources to help others including two pages of social stories.  I linked to the first page of social stories.  The topics range from manners, figures of speech, going to the doctor, or going to school.  Watch out for broken links, though… I’m not sure how recently this page was updated and there are many  broken links.  Even with that said, the free stories that are available might be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Social Stories Resources</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">sensory processing disorder vestibular dysfunction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sensory processing disorder vestibular dysfunction" /><published>2017-02-16T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-16T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction">&lt;h1 id=&quot;sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction&quot;&gt;Sensory Processing Disorder: Vestibular Dysfunction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If proprioception is your 6th sense, then the vestibular system is the 7th sense.  The vestibular system is how we negotiate balance.  It is the intricate system that includes the feedback loop between the inner ear and the brain. If you’ve ever experienced vertigo or dizziness, you understand how it feels to have vestibular problems.  Motion sickness is also a symptom of the vestibular system functioning incorrectly.  Vestibular system is a behind the scenes sense that can absolutely make your life miserable if it isn’t functioning correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypersensitive-vestibular-system&quot;&gt;Hypersensitive Vestibular System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with a hypersensitive vestibular system processes sensory input in a more magnified way.  The sensation they feel when processing vestibular input is uncomfortable so they tend to avoid situations where they might experience this sort of input.  A person who is hypersensitive to vestibular input might be afraid of heights, avoid twirling (especially merry go rounds or swings), and may intensely dislike escalators.  They might also strongly dislike tipping their head over or getting flipped upside down.  Travel might be difficult for them because they might experience motion sickness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hyposensitive-vestibular-system&quot;&gt;Hyposensitive Vestibular System&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction/img_2454/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2454-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hop, hop, hop www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who is less sensitive processing vestibular input may experience this type of input in a less prominent way than the average person.  Their brain doesn’t register the twists and turns in such a strong way. They tend to seek out movement that gives them the vestibular input they need.  Some people will seek out twirling by twisting and turning without developing the sense of dizziness. They might love amusement park rides, is constantly jumping or hopping around.  Also, they love being thrown in the air, swinging high up on swings, or jumping off of furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-can-do&quot;&gt;What You Can Do?&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction/img_2451/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2451-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spinning www.autsimmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you suspect that your child is experiencing any symptoms related to sensory processing disorder, you should contact an OT who can evaluate them. You can find a referral to an OT in your area by visiting the Sensory Processing Disorder Foundation’s web site: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spdfoundation.net&quot; title=&quot;Sensory Processing Disorder Foundation&quot;&gt;http://www.spdfoundation.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities that help improve vestibular dysfunction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try slow swinging activities.  OT’s often have low, wide swings with wide bases that make swinging a low risk activity.  Even so, take swinging activities slow.  If you child isn’t going to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction/img_2452/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2452-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;vestibular movement www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;an OT yet, try swinging for short periods of time at the park.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try rolling your child on a therapy ball.  Make sure you are holding your child firmly, then carefully roll them around on the therapy ball for a few seconds so that they can get the sensation of getting their feet off the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take your child to an amusement park and slowly work your way up to riding on one of the rides.  Make it a fun time and encourage them to go on more as they are ready.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make an obstacle course where you’re required to jump, hop and duck under things.  This gives the child chance to use their vestibular system while having fun.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play a balance game like twister.  Fun and also requires use of the vestibular system to balance on the dots.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ride a bike:  Riding a bike is good for helping almost all of the senses, especially vestibular and proprioceptive.  Balance can really be a struggle for lots of kids.  Giving opportunities to have fun and practice using the vestibular system is important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sit n Spin:  Gives kids a chance to sit and twirl around. Great fun.  Let them twirl as much as they are comfortable with. Click on the following link to visit the amazon site:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hopping ball:  requires balance and motion to control this thing.  It is fun and gives vestibular input.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your favorite ways to improve vestibular functioning?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Sensory Processing Disorder: Vestibular Dysfunction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">sensory disorder vestibular dysfunction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sensory-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sensory disorder vestibular dysfunction" /><published>2017-02-16T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-16T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sensory-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sensory-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction">&lt;h1 id=&quot;sensory-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction&quot;&gt;Sensory Disorder: Vestibular Dysfunction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If proprioception is your 6th sense, then the vestibular system is the 7th sense.  The vestibular system is how we negotiate balance.  It is the intricate system that includes the feedback loop between the inner ear and the brain. If you’ve ever experienced vertigo or dizziness, you understand how it feels to have vestibular problems.  Motion sickness is also a symptom of the vestibular system functioning incorrectly.  Vestibular system is a behind the scenes sense that can absolutely make your life miserable if it isn’t functioning correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypersensitive-vestibular-system&quot;&gt;Hypersensitive Vestibular System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with a hypersensitive vestibular system processes sensory input in a more magnified way.  The sensation they feel when processing vestibular input is uncomfortable so they tend to avoid situations where they might experience this sort of input.  A person who is hypersensitive to vestibular input might be afraid of heights, avoid twirling (especially merry go rounds or swings), and may intensely dislike escalators.  They might also strongly dislike tipping their head over or getting flipped upside down.  Travel might be difficult for them because they might experience motion sickness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hyposensitive-vestibular-system&quot;&gt;Hyposensitive Vestibular System&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction/img_2454/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2454-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hop, hop, hop www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who is less sensitive processing vestibular input may experience this type of input in a less prominent way than the average person.  Their brain doesn’t register the twists and turns in such a strong way. They tend to seek out movement that gives them the vestibular input they need.  Some people will seek out twirling by twisting and turning without developing the sense of dizziness. They might love amusement park rides, is constantly jumping or hopping around.  Also, they love being thrown in the air, swinging high up on swings, or jumping off of furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-can-do&quot;&gt;What You Can Do?&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction/img_2451/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2451-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spinning www.autsimmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you suspect that your child is experiencing any symptoms related to sensory processing disorder, you should contact an OT who can evaluate them. You can find a referral to an OT in your area by visiting the Sensory Processing Disorder Foundation’s web site: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spdfoundation.net&quot; title=&quot;Sensory Processing Disorder Foundation&quot;&gt;http://www.spdfoundation.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities that help improve vestibular dysfunction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try slow swinging activities.  OT’s often have low, wide swings with wide bases that make swinging a low risk activity.  Even so, take swinging activities slow.  If you child isn’t going to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/sensory-processing-disorder-vestibular-dysfunction/img_2452/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2452-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;vestibular movement www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;an OT yet, try swinging for short periods of time at the park.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try rolling your child on a therapy ball.  Make sure you are holding your child firmly, then carefully roll them around on the therapy ball for a few seconds so that they can get the sensation of getting their feet off the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take your child to an amusement park and slowly work your way up to riding on one of the rides.  Make it a fun time and encourage them to go on more as they are ready.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make an obstacle course where you’re required to jump, hop and duck under things.  This gives the child chance to use their vestibular system while having fun.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play a balance game like twister.  Fun and also requires use of the vestibular system to balance on the dots.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ride a bike:  Riding a bike is good for helping almost all of the senses, especially vestibular and proprioceptive.  Balance can really be a struggle for lots of kids.  Giving opportunities to have fun and practice using the vestibular system is important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sit n Spin:  Gives kids a chance to sit and twirl around. Great fun.  Let them twirl as much as they are comfortable with. Click on the following link to visit the amazon site:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hopping ball:  requires balance and motion to control this thing.  It is fun and gives vestibular input.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your favorite ways to improve vestibular functioning?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Sensory Disorder: Vestibular Dysfunction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">sensory processing disorder tactile dysfunction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sensory-processing-disorder-tactile-dysfunction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sensory processing disorder tactile dysfunction" /><published>2017-02-14T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-02-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sensory-processing-disorder-tactile-dysfunction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sensory-processing-disorder-tactile-dysfunction">&lt;h1 id=&quot;sensory-processing-disorder-tactile-dysfunction&quot;&gt;Sensory Processing Disorder: Tactile Dysfunction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactile dysfunction is incredibly frustrating for the person experiencing the problem.  It can come in the form of over sensitivity, under sensitivity or poor perception and discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tactile-defensiveness&quot;&gt;Tactile Defensiveness:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/sensory-processing-disorder-tactile-dysfunction/img_2415/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.autismmom.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/IMG_2415-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tactile Dysfunction www.autismmom.net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Imagine putting on your clothes and they scratch like an old wool sweater on your bare skin.  You have to wear the clothes, because your parents say so.  You go to school and people bumping into you feels like someone is attacking you.  At school you refuse to finger paint because the thought of the paint running down your fingers, under your nails and possibly onto your shirt strikes fear into your heart.  When you get home and you’re eating snack, a bit of banana gets on your finger and your napkin is too dirty to wipe it off immediately.  The panic starts to rise because mom is too busy to get a napkin for you.   When you go to bed falling asleep is difficult because all you can think about is how scratchy the sheets are. You toss and turn because the discomfort is so frustrating and irritating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The description above is an example of what it might be like living with tactile defensiveness.  Tactile defensiveness might come across as OCD but it is actually a problem with how the brain processes tactile information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tactile-hyposensitivity&quot;&gt;Tactile Hyposensitivity:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A child dealing with tactile hyposensitivity is likely more aggressive and rough and tumble than the average kid.  This child is probably playing rough without regard to how he or she might be hurting other children or animals.  They might get bruised up and not seem to care. You might be repeating the phrase, “Stop touching that,” because they must touch every object at the store.  This is the kid who loves to get messy and never seems to notice that they are dirty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A child that is hypersensitive to tactile input seeks dirty, messy and rough play to in order to seek out tactile sensations.  The child’s brain seeks out this type of input in order to process what the sensations feel like.  Seeking this input helps him or her make sense of what it is perceiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poor-tactile-perception-and-discrimination&quot;&gt;Poor Tactile Perception and Discrimination:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frustrations with buttoning or zipping clothes are common among children with poor tactile perception and discrimination.  They may struggle to figure out how hot, cold, big or small something is just by using touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This child’s sense of touch may seem underdeveloped and confused.  Because our own tactile sensation is well developed it might seem strange when a child is unable to use it to it’s full extent. This child’s system is confused and isn’t processing sensory input correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activities-you-can-do&quot;&gt;Activities You Can Do:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you suspect that your child has Sensory Processing Disorder, you should find an occupational therapist qualified to evaluate your child.  The Sensory Processing Disorder Foundation has a link on their site that can connect you to an occupational therapist in your area: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spdfoundation.net&quot; title=&quot;Sensory Processing Disorder Foundation&quot;&gt;http://www.spdfoundation.net &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I am not an occupational therapist, I am a mom of a child with SPD.  The following is a list of activities we have had fun doing with our son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rice/noodle/bean bin:  We have a plastic container filled with our stale rice, beans and noodles.  We take this bin out on the back lawn (and put it on top of blanket to catch the stragglers that fall on the ground), fill it with cars, trucks, plastic people and plastic cups and go to town playing.  Not only does this offer children a chance to seek sensory input in an appropriate way, it also builds a positive relationship and interaction between the adult and child.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Playing with messy household stuff:  We have a couple of those disposable cookie sheets that we take outside and make a mess in them.  We’ve taken shaving cream, baby powder, yogurt, pudding, and corn starch (not at the same time!), dumped it in the cookie sheets, and played in it using trucks (for the child with tactile  defensiveness) or just with our hands.  Great messy fun that can be scaled up or down depending on your child’s needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s in the bag?  Find some “mystery” objects around the house and put them in paper bags.  Ask your child to reach in and feel what the object is.  Without looking, guess what the object is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baking:  Have your child help you with baking.  Bread is a wonderful messy item to make.  Kneading, getting dough on your hands while helping and making something delicious.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play Doh:  You can either make your own or buy some at the store.  Get cookie cutters, a rolling pin or buy a Play-doh kit and play!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Silly Putty, Theraputty, Moonsand, and other squishy substances:  These pre-made squishy substances are fun for everyone to play with.  You can also find recipes for gack and other home-made squishy substances online.  If you child struggles to touch these fun products, you can use cookie cutters, plastic cups or include toys.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brushes of every kind:  We have rough sponges, basting brushes, paint brushes and probably other brushes for our son to press against his skin to get tactile input. Your child may or may not like this sort of pressure.  Check what they like before you buy too many of them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Massagers:  Try using massagers or even an electric tooth brush as a massager.  Some kids enjoy this deep pressure and input.  Others are bothered by it.  Go with your child’s individual likes and needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you child doesn’t have SPD, these activities are fun and exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Sensory Processing Disorder: Tactile Dysfunction</summary></entry></feed>